to get better at music and stop wasting
time by practicing less and how you
should actually spend your time how's
that for a controversial statement I can
hear you mocking me now and it's fair to
question such a statement it almost
calls to mind other famously
controversial musical statements like if
you can play it slowly you can play it
quickly which is actually a perfectly
reasonable starting point but it does
Skip some steps but for now let's focus
on the question how can you get better
with less practice will you just become
a better musician over time with magic
well sad no but stick with me here
because I think there are actually two
ways we can improve by practicing less
and the first has to do with the fact
that many of us would benefit from
examining what does the word practice
really mean what are we actually trying
to achieve when we practice and by
contrasting the word practice with
another word that fits better for a lot
of situations and that word is learning
of course musicians need to practice to
improve there's no question about that
practice and maintenance are fundamental
and I would never suggest that you don't
spend time practicing but consider that
when an experience musician talks about
preparing for a performance or a gig
they might use the word practice like I
have to go practice for my gig but I
found that they're just as likely to say
yeah me too I have to go learn my music
now there's a subtle but crucial
difference there because to me practice
has to do with trying to get better at
things you already basically know how to
do but learning is the acquisition of
new knowledge or skills or at the very
least preparing and becoming familiar
with new material people sometimes treat
these words as interchangeable but
consider the following if you're a
dancer you can practice a dance routine
but you have to learn the choreography
first you can't try to make your steps
and movements faster and smoother if you
haven't learned what the steps and
movements are yet it just wouldn't make
any sense to jump in at full speed if
you don't know what to do first learn
the steps first and then practice them
if you're a cook you can practice making
a recipe but only if you're already
basically familiar with all the
vocabulary and techniques if you're
making chicken pot pie from scratch
you've got to know what mirp is and you
can't run W it if you have no idea what
that is and you've got to know how to
make bamal And Pastry which are recipes
unto themselves so you can't really
practice the recipe until you've learned
all the things the recipe is asking you
to do if you're an actor you can
practice your lines but only if you know
how to pronounce the words in the script
and if you're playing a doctor on a
Starship speaking to a space wizard your
lines might be absolutely filled with
terms and names that are long and
unfamiliar and difficult to read at
first you'll have to spend time working
on how to make those unfamiliar sounds
into familiar sounds that you can
pronounce with ease only then can you
really practice your line and craft your
performance and if you're a musician and
you're working on a piece of music you
first need to understand what the piece
is asking of you that means you need to
know how to physically play all the
notes on your instrument how to read and
interpret the rhythms and what all the
other terms and symbols mean too novice
and intermediate musicians routinely
encounter new notes rhythms or other
musical elements that they have to learn
how to execute most New pieces will have
something new they haven't seen before
but even if you do understand everything
there may be sections that are awkward
or unfamiliar or just really dense with
musical information you might find
yourself struggling to even play the
correct notes because there's just so
many of them and it can be a bit
overwhelming you have to get familiar
enough with the notes that you're not
making a bunch of Errors before you even
worry too much about speed or even
expression you have to learn the piece
before you can practice it practice is
the act of polishing and refining
reinforcing good habits and maintaining
skills and abilities of things you can
already do learning is the process of
acquiring skills knowledge and
understanding in the first place
practice is is walking down a path
wearing it in and moving along it faster
and smoother learning is creating the
Pathways in the first place and if you
try to run really fast while creating A
New Path you might just run into a
tree now you might be saying yeah yeah
yeah learning practicing whatever what's
the difference the goal is the same
sound good and play well so who cares
about what you call the process but I
think there's a real danger to
conflating the two terms because it
seems that some musicians kind of skip
the learning phase and move straight to
the practice phase and they end up
wasting a ton of time they'll play a
piece or passage over and over again at
full Tempo or close to it making the
same or different mistakes each time
with no particular tactic for how to
improve accuracy seemingly just hoping
that it will magically get better and
they might play it 20 times in a row and
then somehow play it correctly mostly by
accident and exclaim I did it but did
they really the thing that comes to mind
when this happens is video games now I'm
not anti-gaming at all I've owned many
gaming systems and continue to spend
many hours gaming I adore a tower
defense game the first Plants vs Zombies
was a hilariously themed Masterpiece but
the thing about games is you only need
to beat a level in a game once in order
to move on you can fail 19 times in a
row succeed once and finally move on to
the next level or maybe beat the whole
game in glorious and deeply satisfying
Triumph but some skills are different in
music if you just played a passage wrong
19 times in a row and finally play it
right once you've still got a 95%
failure rate behind you so what are the
chances that you're going to play it
right the next time I would say not
great and you have to be really careful
because the saying practice makes
perfect really isn't correct if you
practice a mistake you can learn it
really really well have you ever learned
someone's name wrong you probably
hesitated when using their name for
weeks afterwards learning something
wrong can haunt you if you practice the
wrong notes or rhythms you might very
well learn them so be careful because
practice doesn't make perfect practice
makes
permanent if you're choosing between
practicing for accuracy and practicing
for Speed choose accuracy over speed
always because over time your
performance will almost always get
faster and smoother all on its own but
if you practice while only caring about
speed will accuracy increase maybe who
knows only perfect practice makes
perfect if you play a piece even
extremely slowly but accurately all your
teacher can really say to you is that
was great practice it a bunch and make
it faster but if you play it fast and
it's just you know a mess where can you
even begin other than fixing the errors
imagine a restaurant that advertises
super fast service and you order a
burger and fries and the server returns
a few seconds later and excitedly
presents you with a live cow and a raw
potato you'd say what is this and they'd
say your dinner and you say uh this
isn't what I ordered and the server
would say sure it is and you'd say O
Okay it isn't ready yet and the server
would say maybe but wasn't it fast so
the moral of the story for part one of
how to get better by practicing Les is
learn first then practice don't skip the
learning step and jump straight to
practicing because you can't really
practice something until you've learned
it even though some people try they're
mostly just wasting time and maybe even
getting worse whether you're looking at
a small project or a large project
remember that the Journey of a th000
miles begins with a single step for
music start by learning the notes and
rhythms very carefully and accurately
then learn what all the other stuff on
the page means and start to work that in
and then you can practice and polish and
make it good the process doesn't really
change if the pieces short or long but
whatever you do don't practice mistakes
because you might just learn them now
that we've established the importance of
learning versus practice let's look at
the second way to get better at music by
practicing less which is to make time to
learn new things if you're brand new to
music everything is new and you're
constantly in the learning phase you're
learning notation sound production
technique repertoire and all kinds of
vocabulary symbols and Concepts there's
a lot to learn but your songs and
exercises are probably pretty short and
simple covering one or two things at a
time and and you mostly just play each
one a couple of times and move on to the
next thing you need to learn but after
you've learned a few things and you've
got a few tunes and exercises under your
belt it feels really good to play them
and you probably have some favorites
music is so fun and satisfying because
there is a unique Joy of execution it
feels so good to nail a passage and feel
your body and instrument vibrating and
making amazing beautiful awesome sounds
and Everyone likes to do things that
they're good at because it makes us feel
good so we often practice the same songs
and scales and exercises polishing and
refining over and over and over and
while of course music requires
maintenance and repetition we have to be
careful that we don't practice old
things so much that we forget to work on
new things because if you only ever do
the same things you never really grow or
improve think of some other disciplines
learning a language requires new phrases
and vocabulary not just practicing the
same few phrases over and over chefs and
Cooks learn by challenging themselves
with new ingredients new techniques and
new recipes rather than just cooking the
same few dishes over and
over if you're working on Fitness you
need to push yourself to go further
Harder Faster weightlifters know that
you won't get any stronger if you just
keep lifting the same weight over and
over forever you have to increase the
weight to get stronger and Runners and
cyclists know that you have to increase
your speed distance and resistance if
you want to improve your performance and
even if you are already quite fit it's
always good to learn new exercises and
movements try yoga or rock climbing or
parkour it's good for your brain and
your body to work different muscles in
different ways now if you just play for
fun now and then you know a few tunes
and you're happy with that that's
awesome I'm not going to tell you you're
doing music wrong music is the best
maybe we can play together sometime but
if you do want to improve you should
really think about challenging yourself
with new scales New pieces new exercises
and new repertoire not only will new
challenges make you a better musician
and actually help you play Old
repertoire even better I really believe
that humans require growth we don't do
well with stagnation Comfort is
comfortable and we love the familiar but
if you only play the same songs over and
over again without any novelty growth or
Improvement you won't grow or improve
either you'll either get bored and quit
or when you are confronted with a new
challenge you won't know how to approach
it because you only know how to do what
you already know how to do but if you do
make a habit of learning new things and
you learn how to learn you'll realize
that every new challenge is just a
puzzle to be unlocked and understood or
a journey to begin and as gloriously
satisfying as achieving a particular
goal can be that satisfaction will fade
happiness is derived from growth
practice and maintenance is fundamental
but always remember to
grow so that's the second way you can
get better by practicing less don't just
practice the same things that you
already know how to do over and over
forever be sure to make time to learn
and grow with new and challenging
exercises songs and projects finally
let's take a look at how you might want
to structure your time between learning
and practice to improve and grow in both
the short and long term and quick side
note although we just made a great big
deal about the difference between
practice and learning when you spend
time alone on your instrument working on
music virtually everyone calls it
practice or a practice session and
calling it a learning session is only
going to annoy people so feel free to
say practice but we know what you really
mean of course every musician will have
different needs interests and abilities
but here's a general outline that should
be adaptable and useful for most people
your routine should be broken up into
four basic sections warm-up technique
projects and review warm-up is all about
physically preparing to play and it
involves a few different things first
you need to prepare your space adjust
your music stand make sure you have your
music and a pencil and of course
assemble and set up your instrument with
any accessories you'll need next prepare
your body take a few moments to loosen
up and stretch your fingers arms lips
lungs feet whatever you use to actually
play your instrument try to release
tension and get into good posture then
prepare to play make some sounds tune up
and make sure you're feeling good and
sounding good different musicians will
have different needs in this regard some
will be ready in just a few minutes and
some will take a bit longer think of
warmup like boiling a pot of water it
might be fast or slow depending on a few
factors but it really doesn't matter if
you're an expert Chef or brand new to
cooking the water isn't boiling until
it's boiling and you really can't rush
it or skip that step if you do try to
play when you're not warm you probably
won't sound very good everything will be
a bit more difficult and you might as
well try to make spaghetti with cold
water moving on warm-up Blends very well
into the next section which is all about
technique this is where you maintain and
enhance mechanical things like scales
patterns and other instrument specific
dexterity challenges all the things that
make you a better musician by gaining a
better command of your instrument review
old scales to make sure they're still
solid and maybe make them faster and
cleaner and spend time working on new
scales to build your key fluency you
might even want to work on accents
Dynamics articulation or expanding your
upper and lower register every
instrument and musician will have
different needs here but this section is
a bit like running laps or doing
push-ups or eating your vegetables it
may not always be super exciting but
working on technique on a regular basis
will make every other thing you do
easier next is projects this is the main
course of your practice session this
section is all about preparing
repertoire and making progress on
specific pieces or songs and it can be
challenging work practice is kind of
easy because it's familiar material that
you're trying to make even better but
this can be much more effortful because
by definition you're doing things that
you're not very good at yet things that
you either haven't learned or are in the
process of learning so allow yourself to
struggle a bit and maybe sound like you
don't know what you're doing because you
don't yet of course that doesn't mean to
sound bad or practice mistakes but try
not to worry about what the person
outside the practice room thinks of you
with a new piece or difficult section
you may be playing very slowly and
awkwardly and with very little flow and
that's just fine don't just play fast
and hope it gets better practice
deliberately and work it out if you work
hard with attention to detail and
general mindfulness you'll get better
and faster and smoother you may have a
few different projects on the go at
different levels of Readiness the first
two sections are mostly routine but this
section is dynamic and how you approach
each project may vary some things will
be in the very early stages of learning
While others might be further along and
you'll just be working on speed or
expression remember that this section is
about progress just pick something that
isn't performance ready and make it
better than it was the final section
review is kind of like dessert maintain
and revisit repertoire and play things
that you're great at and that you really
love you've put hard work into this
practice session this is the payoff and
after all that hard work on stuff that
you're not very good at it's always a
good idea a to remind yourself of the
things that you are good at music is
fantastic and it can be so much fun and
it's important to remember that
especially when you've just finished
working on a bunch of new and difficult
things so that's how you can get better
by practicing less number one learn
first then practice otherwise you might
just be wasting a ton of time learning
things wrong and number two make time to
learn new things to grow and challenge
yourself rather than just practicing the
same stuff over and over and when you do
sit down with your instrument balance
your time between a proper warmup so you
sound good techniques so you can get
around your instrument better projects
to improve specific pieces and review to
maintain repertoire and have some fun
remember to like comment share and
subscribe hit the bell for notifications
and check the description for links to
more videos and my patreon page thanks
for watching